Finding Aid for the Robert Wheeler Rand Collection Biomed.0402
UCLA Library Special Collections
Robert Wheeler Rand Collection
1912-2004
UCLA Library Special Collections
Rand, Robert W. (Robert Wheeler)
Biomed.0402
11.6 Linear Feet 5 cartons, 2 boxes, 2 flat boxes, 2 card file boxes, and 1 small lantern slide box
A collection of documents, publications, 35 mm and glass slides, and films chronicling Dr. Robert Rand's career as clinical neurosurgeon, researcher into innovative techniques of cancer treatments and microsurgery, and entrepreneur of medical equipment. Textual coverage of his extensive publications and lectures is sparse, except for the volumes of "Autobiography..." and "Academic History..." written by Rand. The visual material is extensive, however, consisting of circa 4500 35mm slides and 13 films. Some papers, mementos, and glass lantern slides belonging to Carl Wheeler Rand, M.D., father of Robert Rand and also an eminent neurosurgeon, are part of the collection.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Series 6 of this collection (boxes 9-12) is restricted due to patient confidentiality protocols.
In order to access materials that are protected under HIPAA (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act) or for which there is sensitive health information, please submit a research protocol to Library Special Collections at speccoll@library.ucla.edu.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
The materials were a gift to the UCLA Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library from Robert W. Rand, M.D., 2009.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973076663606533
Biography
Robert Wheeler Rand was born in Los Angeles in 1923, son of Carl Wheeler Rand, M.D., a neurosurgeon, and Katherine Humphrey Rand, a former nurse. While a student at Harvard University he was drafted into the U.S. Navy V-12 Program, and under that program finished his pre-med studies at UCLA. Under orders he attended the University of Southern California School of Medicine as a Navel Cadet, and received his M.D. degree in 1947. In 1954, during the Korean War, Dr. Rand was recalled to naval service for two years.
After leaving medical school Dr. Rand entered the University of Michigan surgical training program as an Intern, Assistant Resident in Surgery, and Resident in Neurosurgery at the University Hospital. He continued in Michigan to earn an M.S. in Surgery and a Ph.D. in Anatomy with Dr. Elizabeth Crosby, and became an Instructor in Surgery and Anatomy until 1952. After a short interval of clinical practice with his father back in Los Angeles, Dr. Rand was recruited in 1953 to join the Division of Neurosurgery at the new UCLA School of Medicine. A severe hepatitis attack in 1959 required a lengthy recuperation period for Dr. Rand, which he utilized for a sabbatical year in Paris to study stereotaxic surgery techniques with Professor Jean Talairach. Dr. Rand remained at UCLA until his retirement in 1990. In 1974 he added J.D. to his list of degrees.
Dr. Rand's curriculum vitae (latest version, in his "Academic History...") presents an impressive overview of his career. In addition to teaching activities at UCLA, it lists 398 lectures, addresses, scientific presentations and exhibits, the publication of eight books and 239 articles, 65 abstracts, and a lengthy list of research projects. He produced important contributions to stereotaxic neurosurgery, to fetal brain tissue transplantation for Parkinson disease, to the use of the Leksell gamma knife in treatment of brain tumors, to microneurosurgery, and to the use of cryosurgery, electromagnetic hyperthermia, and infusion of Interleukin or other toxins for tumor treatments in many body locations. He was instrumental in creating a Neuroscience Institute at the Good Samaritan Hospital in Los Angeles, and the The John Wayne Cancer Institute Neuro-oncology Program in Santa Monica, CA.
In addition to teaching, clinical practice, and research, Dr. Rand also found time and energy to be an entrepreneur, holding patents and forming companies in medical and surgical instrumentation. He is presently residing in Santa Monica, California.
Scope and Content
After his retirement from UCLA Dr. Rand authored two autobiographical volumes, included in this collection, about his personal and professional lives. The first provides anecdotal accounts of family, education, exceptional patients, and new surgical techniques and equipment invented and/or tested. The second includes copies of his most important clinical and research papers, important correspondence, patents, and a very complete curriculum vitae. The collection's other textual materials add rather sparsely to Dr. Rand's clinical and research history, but they do document very well his commercial ventures with Nova Therapeutic Systems Inc. and other enterprises. Included are patents, business and marketing plans and presentations, and business correspondence. One small series of folders contains outlines, drafts, and correspondence related to creating a "medical thriller" novel or screenplay based on a neuroscience plot.
The bulk of the collection consists of visual materials, mainly 35 mm slides and 35 mm motion pictures. They cover a variety of clinical practice and clinical research situations, many of which, unfortunately, were not identified. Access to any materials which name specific patients is restricted; contact the UCLA History and Special Collections for the Sciences Division for further information.
Two cartons contain a variety of surgical instruments from two generations of neuroscientist, Dr. Robert W. Rand and his father, Dr. Carl W. Rand. Also included are diplomas, certificates, mementos, and glass lantern slides that belonged to Dr. Carl Rand.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Missing Title
Series 1. Personal Materials, 1948-2004. 5 folders
Series 2. Professional Materials, 1955-2000. 103 folders (4500 35mm slides), 51 glass slides, 4 objects, 5 films, 3 tapes, 2 cartons instruments
Series 3. Patents, Commercial Activities, 1987-2004. 12 folders
Series 4. Materials for a Novel or Screenplay, 2000-2003. 5 folders
Series 5. Carl Wheeler Rand, M.D., 1912-1940. 8 folders
Series 6. Restricted Materials. 25 folders with ca. 670 35 mm slides, 8 films, 63 glass lantern slides
Neurosurgery -- Biography.; Neurosurgeons -- California -- Biography.; Gamma Knife Radiosurgery -- History.; Rand, Carl W. (Carl Wheeler); Rand, Robert W. (Robert Wheeler) -- Archives
- Personal Materials., 1948-2004; Series 1.; 5 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Full curriculum vitae, two massive volumes of autobiographical history and academic achievements
  - Curriculum vitae., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    personal information, awards, teaching activities, professional activities and offices, exhibits, motion pictures, lectures-addresses-scientific presentations, research projects, bibliography (227 articles & chapters, 8 books), grants and support for research
  - "The Autobiography of Robert Wheeler Rand, Ph.D., J.D., M.D."., 2003; 1 bound volume (Box 1, Folder 2)
    short descriptions of family history, word portraits of family members; vignettes of childhood, education, and career; descriptions and remembrances of teachers and colleagues; desciptions of new surgical techniques and equipment invented and/or tried by RWR; curriculum vitae [later version than Folder 1]; photocopies of photographs [unidentified]
    General note
    dedicated "...to my beautiful wife, Helen, and to my wonderful sons, Carl and Richard."
  - "The Academic History of Robert Wheeler Rand, Ph.D., J.D., M.D."., 2004; 1 bound volume (Box 1, Folder 3)
    photocopies of Rand publications, patents, letters, announcements, etc., pertaining to his clinical and research achievements and inventions; curriculum vitae and full bibliography
    the volume is "Dedicated to my wife Helen Pierce Rand"
  - Diplomas., 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Doctor of Medicine, University of Southern California, 1948, photocopy (original housed in oversized Box 6, Folder 1); Doctor of Philosophy in Anatomy, Univ. of Michigan, 1952 (photocopy); Board certification in Neurological Surgery, The American Board of Neurological Surgery, 1954
  - Correspondence with Prof. Jean Talairach., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Dr. Rand spent several months with Dr. Talairach in Paris in 1960 learning new techniques in stereotaxic neurosurgery
- Professional Materials., 1955-2000; Series 2.; 103 folders (4500 35mm slides), 51 glass slides, 4 objects, 5 films, 3 tapes, 2 cartons instruments
  - Manuscripts and Publications., 1964-2000; Subseries 1.; 16 folders
    Very spotty coverage of scientific output
    - "Cryosurgery", edited by Robert W. Rand, Arthur P. Rinfret, Hans von Leden. Springfield, Ill., Charles C Thomas., 1968; 428 pp (Box 1, Folder 6)
      volume with Robert W. Rand's signature
    - Cryosurgery., 1982, 1988, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      correspondence; reprint of "Cryolumpectomy for carcinoma of the breast"; "Breast Cancer Cryolumpectomy: the Rand Operation" - four-page brochure issued by Women Against Cancer, Los Angeles; three color photo sheets of brain scans
    - "Stereotaxic cryohypophysectomy versus transnasal-transsphenoidal operation in pituitary tumors"., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      typed abstract
    - "New concepts in the treatment of breast cancer and uterine cancer"., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      eight typed pages, giving layman description of the use of cryosurgery and thermomagnetic surgery
      written note on title page: "File in brochure folder"
    - "Low frequency electromagnetic hyperthermic hysteresis in neoplasms"., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      23-page typed research plan, with figures and captions, with investigators Rand, H.D. Snow and D. Elliott
    - Electromagnetic hyperthermia., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      15 mounted illustrations with captions, plus others, pertaining to experiments with canine kidney and thoracic tumors treated by heating injected ferromagnetic materials
    - Stereotaxic radiosurgery - gamma knife., 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      "Leksell stereotactic radiosurgery in the treatment of eye melanoma" - reprint from "Neurological Research", 1987; "Leksell gamma knife treatment of tic douloureux" - 7 p. typed manuscript; "Gamma knife thalamotomy and pallidotomy in patients with movement disorders - preliminary results" -10 p. typed manuscript, with two cover letters; "The cobalt scalpel" - 9 p. typed manuscript
    - Neurovascular compression/decompression., 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      two typed drafts, titled: "Neurovascular compression of cranial nerves", "Hemifacial spasm: the Gardner neurovascular decompression operation", and one untitled draft on compression in vestibular disorders
    - "Transmeatal operation of Rand-Kurze for acoustic neuromas"., undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Parotid gland transplant following hypophysectomy"., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      memo from Rand and Dr. Gunnar Heuser suggesting a human trial to the UCLA School of Medicine Human Use Committee
    - Microneurosurgery., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      a few draft pages and figure captions, possibly for an edition of "Microneurosurgery", ed. by Rand, published by Mosby
    - Instruments for microsurgery., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      draft article: "A solid state pulsed coagulating diathermy instrument", by P.G. Petty, A.J. Lim, R. Stahl; short description of a "Nylon mono filament suture sealer", by Werner P.Schulz, with photographs; handwritten figure captions, by Rand
    - "Neurotrauma and medical malpractice"., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      typed draft, 2d revision
      not published
    - Publication reprints and photocopies., 1964-2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      fourteen reprints
    - Oral presentations., 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      announcements and programs
    - Gershwin lecture., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      reprint of "The case of George Gershwin", by Bengt Ljunggren (1982); several figures of brain gliomas from Rand; handwritten note: "Dr. Rand did not give lecture because of family emergency..."
  - Memberships, Honors, Objects., 1955-1990; Subseries 2.; 7 folders, 4 objects, 2 cartons
    Certificates and objects, cartons of medical and surgical instruments
    - The Western Neurosurgical Society., 1955; 24 x 29 cm plaque (Box 1, Folder 22)
      certifying Dr. Rand as a founding member of the Society
    - The Society of Neurological Surgeons., 1967; 25.5 x 30.5 cm plaque (Box 1, Folder 23)
      certifying Dr. Rand's election to the Society
    - Societatis Chirurgicae Americanae., 1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      certificate of membership
    - International College of Surgeons., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      certificate of election as a Fellow in Neurological Surgery of the College
    - College International de Chirurgiens. XX Biennial Congress, Athens., 1976 May 23-27; sculpted female head in classical Greek style on a 4 x 4 x 3 cm stone base (Box 3, Folder Object 1)
    - American Society for Stereotactic and Functional Neurosurgery., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      certificate of Dr. Rand's election as an active member of the Society
    - XIX Congreso Latino-Americano de Neurocirurgia, Guayaquil, Ecuador., 1981 September 27; 10 cm diameter silver metal tray (Box 3, Folder Object 2)
    - The Western Neurosurgical Society., 1982; 30.5 x 23 x 6 cm plaque with gavel (Box 1, Folder 26)
      proclaims Dr. Rand as President of the Society
    - Joint Section on Tumors, AANS/CNS., 1990 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Certificate of membership in the Society
    - Okayama University Medical School. Medal., undated; bronze, 72 mm + box (Box 3, Folder Object 3)
      obverse: "Okayama University Medical School/ founded in 1870", with map of Japan highlighting Okayama; reverse: "In Honor of Lecture/ to/ Prof. Robert W. Rand", with two flying cranes, building and hills; in presentation case
    - Medal of Egas Moniz., undated; bronze, 72 mm (Box 3, Folder Object 4)
      obverse: "Professor Egas Moniz - MCMXLIV", with portrait (facing right); reverse: "Angiografia/ Cerebral/ 1927/Leucotomia/ Pre-frontal/ 1936", with tree branch with leaves
    - Surgical instruments and equipment., undated (Box 4)
      ca. 65 instruments from various periods, a few unused and still in original wraps, plus one instrument tray; Neuromod Stimulator, from MEDTRONIC, USA, in plastic box
    - Surgical instruments and equipment., undated (Box 5, Folder Objects #2, 3)
      Object #2: plastic box of surgical instruments; Object #3: Stereotaxic attachments in plastic box
  - Slides., 1967-2000; Subseries 3.; 74 folders with ca. 4500 35mm slides; 1 box with 51 glass lantern slides; more slides in RESTRICTED
    Most of the slides are undated and without specific identification
    - Rabbit no.5., 1984; text and 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 1)
      data sheets on three rabbits; ca. 180 slides of Rabbit no. 5 pre- and post-radiosurgery of eye melanoma
    - Rabbits no.8 and 9., 1984; text and 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 2)
      data sheets; ca. 220 slides of Rabbit no. 8 pre- and post-radiosurgery of eye melanoma, 1 slide for Rabbit 9
    - Rabbit no. 12., 1984; text and 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 3)
      data sheets; ca. 200 slides of Rabbit no. 12 pre- and post-radiosurgery of eye melanoma
    - Eyes., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 4)
      ca. 200 unidentified slides
      possibly duplicates of the above 3 folders
    - Stereotaxic brain surgery in rabbit eye melanoma., 1984; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 5)
      one text slide, 19 whole eyes, tissue sections
    - Human eye., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 6)
      68 slides; see also restricted folder: "Orbital tumors"
    - Cat brain., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 7)
      23 slides of fixed brain sections
    - Bile duct., 1967-1968; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 8)
      14 slides of dog experiments, 7 slides of historical text and illustrations
    - Dog experiments., 1981-1985, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 9)
      ca. 55 slides on lungs, pituitary, other
    - Monkey experiments., 1975; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 10)
      10 slides
    - Infusion therapy for tumors - IL4 toxin., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 11)
      54 slides of text and tables; see also restricted folder: "Infusion therapy"
    - Immunotherapy for tumors., 1995; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 12)
      40 slides
    - Acoustic neuromas, other tumors., 1974, 1980-1985; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 13)
      one set of commercial slides; series of 1980 slides; ca. 180 slides
      see also restricted folder: "Identified patients - acoustic neuromas"
    - Pituitary tumors., 1972-1976; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 14)
      ca. 25 slides
      see also: 1. restricted folder: "Identified patients - pituitary tumors" [Box 4, Folder 8]; 2. Cryohypophysectomy, [Box 2, Folder 17]
    - Hematoporphyrin derivative photoradiation therapy., 1982; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 15)
      17 slides
    - Cryosurgery., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 16)
      ca. 75 slides, many of illustrations from "Cryosurgery", 1968, edited by Rand
    - Cryohypophysectomy for diabetic retinopathy., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 17)
      60 slides
    - Cryohypophysectomy for other conditions., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 18)
      12 slides
    - Cryosurgery for breast cancer., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 19)
      ca. 55 slides
      see also "Cryolumpectomy", Box 2, Folder 20
    - Cryolumpectomy., 1984; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 20)
      labeled "first cryolumpectomy patient, 77 year old woman"; 93 slides
      see also "Cryosurgery for breast cancer", Box 2, Folder 19
    - History of breast cancer., 1986; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 21)
      10 slides, portraits and illustrations
    - Breast self-examination., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 22)
      20 slides of text and illustrations
    - Taxol (paclitaxel) injection for breast cancer., 2000; 35 mm slides, booklet (Box 2, Folder 23)
      company-produced 20 slides, printed booklet, and patient information sheet concerning the product
    - Mouse mammary glands., 1984; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 24)
      ca. 115 slides of dissection demonstrations/laboratory exercises [?]; original folder was labeled "USC Med. Day"
    - Mouse breast cancer., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 25)
      ca. 50 slides
    - Uterine tumors., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 26)
      11 slides
    - Acromegaly., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Spine, spinal cord., 1980, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 28)
      ca. 60 slides; see also restricted folder: "Spinal cord"
    - Hemoblastoma of spinal cord., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Arteriovenous malformation of spinal cord., 1986; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 30)
      ca. 30 slides
    - Arteriovenous malformations., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 31)
      ca. 50 slides; see also restricted folder: "Identified patients - arteriovenous malformations"
    - Carotid artery, cerebral arteries - endarterectomy, bypass., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 32)
      ca. 40 slides
    - Aneurysms., 1976, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 33)
      ca. 45 slides
    - Parkinsonism: fetal cell transplants and other therapies., 1992-1996; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 34)
      ca. 80 slides; text, operations, result graphs, brain scans
      see also restricted folder: "Parkinsonism"
    - Thalamotomy for tic douloureux., 1992; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 35)
      40 slides of brain scans
      see also restricted folder: "Identified patients - tic douloureux"
    - Brain MRIs., 1982, 1987, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 36)
      19 Technicare slides; 24 Magneton (Siemens) slides of cerebral circulation; ca. 150 unidentified slides
    - Skull visualization., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Brain cross sections., 1974-1978, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 38)
      21 slides
    - Anatomical illustrations., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 39)
      25 slides
    - Epilepsy., 1986, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 40)
      ca. 80 slides, mostly on temporal lobe epilepsy; see also restricted folder: "Identified patients - epilepsy"
    - Nasopharyngeal angiofibroma., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 41)
      6 slides
    - Mouse kidney., 1984; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 42)
      ca. 90 slides
    - Mouse kidney [?]., 1984, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 43)
      ca. 50 slides, unlabeled
    - Rabbit kidney., 1971-1978; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 44)
      24 slides
    - Dog kidney and unspecified., 1978, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 45)
      ca. 60 slides
    - Hyperthermia, thermomagnetic surgery., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 46)
      ca. 80 slides, animal and human surgery
    - Cancer survival rates, Treatment comparisons., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 47)
      ca. 50 slides, covering female endocrine tumors, glioblastomas, astrocytomas; sources unidentified
    - Data tables., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 48)
      series of 22 tables with treatment and outcome information on cases with various tumors and conditions - source unidentified
    - Tissue sections., 1981, 1984, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 49)
      ca. 130 slides, unidentified
    - Leksell gamma knife., undated. 1971; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 50)
      ca. 40 slides of explanatory text, and 8 illustrations from "Stereotaxis and radiosurgery: an operative system" by Lars Leksell, Springfield, Ill., Charles C Thomas
    - The Cobalt scalpel., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 51)
      43 text and operation slides
    - Gamma knife - text slides., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Gamma knife surgery - brain scans., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 53)
      ca. 60 slides; see also restricted folder: "Identified patients - gamma knife"
    - Gamma knife surgery - thalamotomy for pain syndrome., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Gamma knife surgery - preparation of patients for surgery., 1979, 1982, 1991; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 55)
      ca. 100 slides
    - Gamma knife surgery - operating room scenes., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 2, Folder 56)
      56 slides
    - Gamma knife surgery - various., 1980-1990; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 1)
      ca. 230 slides
    - CAT brain scans., 1980; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 2)
      23 slides
    - Pain., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 3)
      75 slides on anatomy, therapeutic methods and techniques; majority are labeled
    - Trigeminal nerve., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 4)
      8 slides
    - Patient #016592., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 5)
      15 slides
    - Operative techniques., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 6)
      ca. 100 slides, including 20 slides of colored illustrations from an unidentified published source, showing open brain surgery technique
    - Operating room scenes., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 7)
      38 slides
      see also "Gamma knife - Operating room scenes" [Box 2, Folder 56]
    - "Microneurosurgery", edited by Robert W. Rand. 3rd ed. Mosby: St. Louis., 1985; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 8)
      three series selected from the published illustrations: 43 slides from chapters 3-5,13,27,35,40,42; 47 slides from chapters 17-18, 20-21; 67 slides from chapters 26,41-43
    - Microsurgery - electron microscope., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 9)
      30 slides